So we are looking at right looking at multi-armed
bandit problems, we looked at a couple of
ways of solving it so essentially you try
to keep an estimate of the value function
around, right the value function is the expected
payoff that you get for pulling an arm, right
you keep an estimate of the value function
around and then you behave in some exploratory
fashion with respect to that value function
that you have right.
So either you do epsilon greedy or you do
soft max or something and, you get some kind
of asymptotic guarantees correct, yes okay
good, we also spoke about other forms of optimality
so one of them we spoke about was regret optimality
so regret optimality is what, reducing the
total I mean or increasing the total reward
that you get over the process of learning
right, so the initial loss that you get due,
to the exploration you want to minimize.
So that I come as close as possible to the
optimal case as quickly as possible right
so that is essentially what regret is all
about and, so we will start by looking at
one algorithm which in some sense has become
the popular most popular bandit algorithm
around right now, because it's so easy to
implement and also gives you not too bad regret
bounds okay is called the upper confidence
bond, the upper confidence bound algorithm
or the UCB algorithm, okay.
So I will use slightly different notation
today, right not not too different I will
try to as much as possible I will try to translate
the fly, okay to the notation that is used
in the textbook right so even though I will
give we will be giving you some papers to
read, you can take care of linking the UCB
paper and the median elimination paper and
other things right, and we will be giving
you some papers to read and the notation in
the papers will be very different okay.
You probably have to spend like half an hour
just trying to understand the notation, but
when I am explaining it in class to the extent
possible I will try to map it to the notations
used in the book right, so that you have one
uniform set of things that you can keep track
of throughout right, the changes are the following
right, I am going to assume that there are
capital K arms right, earlier I was assuming
there were n arms but it turns out the reason
I want to change n is we are going to now
talk about a notion of time right.
So now so they are going to be pulls at every
time instant and so on so forth and this should
be familiar to electrical engineer, so if
time is discrete you denote it by n if time
is continuous you denote it by t right so
I want to be able to denote discrete time,
so I want to use n for discrete time okay
and so we will save n for discrete time and
I will not use it for the number of arms,
so that is the reason I switch to K okay,
assume there are K arms and so as before with
each arm there is associated some arbitrary
probability distribution which.
I don't know that whenever I pull an arm I
will get a sample drawn from that probability
distribution it could be Bernoulli it could
be Gaussian right it could be poisson we do
not know what distribution it is but according
to that distribution we will get a, payoff
right and what else do we did we assume last
time there is the expectation given for that
distribution right now yeah we assume that
the distribution is stationary.
It is not going to change with time right
and that there is an expectation associated
with that distribution which we will denote
by Q star of A right, when you say Q star
of A it is the expectation for pulling arm
A ok.
Is it clear, so here is the UCB algorithm
so assume there are K arms so the initialization
phase is play each arm at least once right
play each arm once right, you have to pull
every arm at least one time you cannot do
better than that agree right, if I never pull
the arm I do not know anything about that
arm.
So I need to pull each arm at least one so
that is the least so we start off with that
and then we do the following in a loop, so
you remember what Qj is, it is the estimated
payoff as expected payoff right so this is
average reward that we'll be maintaining right
this is a value function right for arm j so
Qj is the estimate that I have at time n right
Qj estimate I have at time n for arm j.
So essentially what I am doing is I am taking
whatever is the current estimate right, and
I am adding this expression to that right,
and then I am playing the arm that gives me
the highest value for this total expression
right, so the way to think about this is the
following I will come back to this we will
show things more precisely later, but let
us assume that this is my, Q of arm one right
whatever is some scale this the x-axis, I
mean the x-axis let us assume is the arm index
and the y-axis is the expected payoff right.
So that is Q1 then I have Q2 say Q3 and Q4,
let us say I have four arms right so what
the idea behind upper confidence bound is
to say that hey, I am not going to use just
the estimated expectations so far right, so
I've actually drawn many samples right I can
use the samples that I have drawn so far to
figure out, what is the confidence with which,
I can say that this is the expectation right.
So you can you can think of giving some kind
of a bound around this you can say that ok,
this is the expectation I have right but the
true value of Q1 or Q star1 right the true
value of Q star 1 is going to lie within that
band right, so intuitively you can see that
the more number of times have sampled arm
one the smaller is this going to be, right
if I have taken a lot of samples then I'm
more confident about the expectation that
I am going to tell you right we know that
as the number of samples tends to infinity
this Q will converge to Q star.
So we know that that Q1 will converge to Q
star 1 if number of times I have sampled one
goes to infinity, so the more the number of
samples I draw the narrower will be this band
of uncertainty right, so likewise I will have
a band like this for Q2 right I will have
a band like this for Q3, I will have a band
like this for Q4, so what arm do am I suggesting
that you take now, I am saying take arm one
that is what essentially UCB tells you right.
So why do you think this kind of scenario
might have happened I might have chosen arm
4 a lot of times because it seems to have
a higher value, so my uncertainty in the value
of arm 4 has come down all lot right, but
arm one I have not taken enough times, arm
3 obviously I have not taken enough times,
but I am really not inclined to take arm 3
anymore because given my current state of
uncertainty right, the probability that arm
3 will be higher than this end right, it is
very small that even though my uncertainty
of arm 3 is very high I am not inclined to
take that arm, because the chance that it
will truly be high the chance that it will
truly be high is very small right.
While for arm 1 the chance that it might be
better than arm 4 is fairly decent so this
interval I am telling you is some kind of
bound, that says that with very high probability
right the true value of Q1, will lie within
this bound, that means there is a chance that
it will lie here which case it can be higher
than Q4 right, so I will take this if I take
this a few more times and let us say after
some time, my estimate moves up like this
but my
estimate moves up a little bit but my bounds
also shrink right.
Now it might not look attractive compared
to Q4, so I will go back to taking Q4 right,
so that is why you can see in this expression
I have the total number, of samples I have
drawn off arm j right, where Nj is the number
of times I have sampled arm j so the larger
the Nj the smaller this expression is going
to become, ok the larger the number of samples
I draw the smaller this expression will become,
therefore this interval will keep coming down.
Whats that, yeah that is more like a normalizing
term right it is there in all the expressions
all the values right all the intervals that
you compute so it is not relatively it is
not going to matter but you will need it to
show some results later, so the algorithm
itself clear right, so to explain things here
n is essentially the number of times I have
played arm.
so for any arm Nj a number of times I have
played arm j okay.
So you have that pictorial description of
what this algorithm is doing great, so what
is nice about this algorithm it is a very
very simple algorithm you saw that right,
there is nothing about it all you need to
do is apart from keeping track of Qj you have
to keep track of Nj, as well which you were
anyway doing if you were doing that incremental
update right, if you remember last class we
wrote the incremental update so the step size
was any way related to Nj.
So the only additional overhead would be if
you have been using constant alpha for your
updates you will have to remember NJ in addition
otherwise it is exactly the same thing like
we did for epsilon greedy, so instead of randomly
deciding which action to take for exploration
you do not do any exploration also the random
the random number generator also has gone
now right so this is a very deterministic
algorithm right.
So what is so great about it yeah, Qj no because
the other term might be a very small term
Q might be a very large then, doesn't matter
why does it matter, they like QJ like the
expected payoffs can be something 10 ah that
way okay, fine fine fine fine fine yeah, so
all of this this this particular form of expression
does assume that the rewards are bounded between
0 and 1 right, so yeah I will come to that
in a minute.
So yeah you are right, so then you can rescale
the rewards if you want to write as long as
all the rewards are positive so you can rescale
them to lie between 0 and 1 but if you have
negative rewards you'll have to think about
how you would want to do this.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resources Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved